Mohamed Said Mahmoud

Researcher of Environmental Biotechnology

Tel: +202- 01157927521 E-mail: mphdmicro2012@yahoo.com

11, Elnagar avenue from Elhoria st. - Elmataria, Cairo, Egypt



Date and Place of Birth

October 28, 1982

Nationality

Egyptian

Marital state

Married

Candidate Profile

Over ten-years of scientific career in multiple locations including Faculty of Science at Al-Azhar University, Hot Laboratory Center at Egyptian Atomic Energy Authority (EAEA) and Sanitary & environmental Institute (SEI) at Housing and Building National Research Center (HBRC) with academic excellence and scientific success certificate. Experience gained from several projects in field of water and wastewater analysis and water quality assessment, Lecturer director in different training courses. Member of Ocean Expert (Directory of Marine and Freshwater Professionals), American Chemical Society (ACS), Royal Society of Chemistry (RSC), American Association for Science and Technology (AASCIT), We The Microbiologist (WTM), the International Association of Engineers (IAENG), the New York Academy of Sciences, International Association of Hydrological Sciences (IAHS), International Society for Environmental Information Sciences (ISEIS), Society of Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry (SETAC) in Africa and editorial review board member at the World Academy of Science, Engineering & Technology (WASET), Reviewer at Research on Chemical Intermediates (RINT) and Brazilian Archives of Biology & Technology. My research interests cover treatment of water and wastewater using different eco-friendly and law cost environmental materials including biological, chemical, physical and mathematical modeling. Prepare and teach course materials.

Education

Academic	University/School	General	specific	Location	Grade	Year
Degree		Specialization:	Specialization			
Ph.D.	Faculty of	Microbiology	Applied	Cairo,	Awarded	April
Science	Science, Al-Azhar		Mycology	Egypt		2012
	University					
Professor	EL-Tayieb, M.M.; El- Shafei, M.M (Housing and Building National Research Center)					
Advisors:	El-Sheikh, H.H. and Abdel-Ghany, T.M. (Faculty of Science, Al-Azhar University)					
Topic:	Biotechnological application of wastewater treatment using fungi					
M.Sc.	Faculty of	Microbiology	Applied	Cairo,	Awarded	June,
Science	Science, Al-		Mycology	Egypt		2009
	Azhar University					
Professor	Abdel-Razek, A.S. and Mahmoud, S.A. (Atomic Energy Authority)					
Advisors:	El-Sheikh, H.H. and Abdel-Ghany, T.M. (Faculty of Science, Al-Azhar University)					
Topic:	Biotechnology of liquid radioactive and hazardous wastes treatment using certain fungi					
B.Sc.	Faculty of			Cairo,	Excellent with	May,
Science	Science, Al-	Microbiology- Chemistry		Egypt	honor degree	2004
	Azhar University					

Working Experiences

Job Title	Employer	Location	Year		
Researcher	China National Pulb and Paper Research Institute	Sinolight Plaza, 4# Qiyang Road, Wangjing, Chaoyang Disdrict, Beijing, China Phone: 86-10-64778065 Cell: 86-15101180352 Email: chgong1231@163.com	2/2017 - Current		
Job Description	Researcher for lignocellulose-based biorefinery.				
Researcher	Sanitary and Environmental Institute (SEI), Housing and Building National Research Center (HBRC)	87 El-Tahrir St., Dokki, Giza, 11511, Egypt. P.O. Box: 1770 Cairo Tel: (+202)37617102, 37617092 Fax: (+202)33351564, 37628736 e.mail: hbrc@hbrc.edu.eg https://www.hbrc.edu.eg	12/2012 -Current		
Job Description	Technical manager of Chemistry lab for water and wastewater and Lead a team of three graduate students for different research projects in Wastewater treatment and Drinking water.				
Assistant Lecturer	Sanitary and Environmental Institute (SEI), Housing and Building National Research Center (HBRC)	87 El-Tahrir St Dokki, Cairo, Egypt	6/2009- 12/2012		
Job Description	Proceed different water analysis and prepare my Ph.D. research work				
M. Sc. fellowship	Scientific Research and Technology Academy	Waste Management Facilities, Radiation Protection Department, Egyptian Atomic Energy Authority (EAEA) – Egypt	12/2005- 12/2008		
Job Description	Proceed different water analysis and prepare my M.Sc. research work				
Demonstrator	Botany and Microbiology department, Faculty of Science, , Al-Azhar University	Cairo, Egypt	second semester of 2006		
Job Description	Prepare and teach practical courses for the first class of Biological Division including many courses (bacterial counts, biochemical analysis, enzymatic assays and Bacterial Taxonomy)				

<u>Awards</u>

Had a Scientific Success Certificate from Al-Azhar University-Faculty of Science

Publications

Journal Articles

- 1. **Mohamed S. Mahmoud, Mohamed K. Mostafa, Samah A. Mohamed, Neama A. Sobhy, Mahmoud Nasr, (2017).** "Bioremediation of red azo dye from aqueous solutions by Aspergillus niger strain isolated from textile wastewater" Journal of Environmental Chemical Engineering 5: 547–554.
- 2. **Mahmoud, M.S. (2016).** "Decolorization of Certain Reactive Dye from Aqueous Solution using Baker's Yeast (*Saccharomyces cerevisiae*) Strain" HBRC Journal 12(1): 88–98, April 2016. doi:10.1016/j.hbrcj.2014.07.005.
- 3. **Mohamed K. Mostafa, Mohamed S. Mahmoud and Robert W. Peters (2016).** "Use of statistical analyses to assess water quality at the Damietta branch of the Nile river, Egypt" J. of Environment and Biotechnology Research, 2(1): 16-26.

- 4. **Mahmoud, M.S. and Samah A. Mohamed (2015).** "Calcium alginate as an ecofriendly supporting material for Baker's yeast strain in chromium bioremediation" Elsevier Editorial System (tm) for HBRC Journal, doi:10.1016/j.hbrcj.2015.06.003.
- 5. **Abdeen, Z; Mohammad, S.G; Mahmoud, M.S. (2015).** "Adsorption of Mn (II) ion on polyvinyl alcohol/chitosan dry blending from aqueous solution" Environmental Nanotechnology, Monitoring & Management, 3: 1–9.
- 6. **Maha Mostafa El Shafei and Mahmoud M.S. (2015).** "Enhanced sorptive reduction of phosphate ions from wastewater using activated red mud" Seventh International Conference On Nano-Technology In Construction, Sharm El-Sheikh, Egypt, 2015.
- 7. **Mahmoud, M.S. (2014).** "Banana Peels as an Eco-Sorbent for Manganese Ions" International Journal of Biological, Veterinary, Agricultural and Food Engineering, **8(11):** 1065-1071, eISSN: 1307-6892.
- 8. **Abou Elmagd, A. M. and Mahmoud, M.S., (2014)** "Tannery Wastewater Treatment Using Activated Sludge Process System (Lab Scale Modeling)" International Journal of Engineering and Technical Research (IJETR) ISSN: 2321-0869, **2(5)**, May 2014
- 9. **Mahmoud, M.S. and Abou Elmagd, A. M., (2013)** "Characterization of alginate polymer and its application in copper removal from liquid wastes" Journal of American Science 9(11): 432-439. http://www.jofamericanscience.org.
- 10. **EL-Tayieb**, **M.M.**; **El- Shafei**, **M.M.** and **Mahmoud**, **M.S.**, **(2013)** "The role of alginate as polymeric material in treatment of tannery wastewater" International Journal of Science and Technology **2**(2): 218-224.
- 11. El- Shafei, M.M.; El-Sheikh, H.H.; EL-Tayieb, M.M. and Mahmoud, M.S., (2012) "Treatment of tannery wastewater using free and immobilized cells of sodium hydroxide treated *A. niger* strain" 2nd International Conference and Exhibition Sustainable Water Supply and Sanitation (SWSSC) held during 3 –5 December 2012 at the Cairo In'l Conference Center in Cairo–Egypt.
- 12. Abdel-Razek, A.S.; Abdel-Ghany, T.M.; Mahmoud, S.A.; El-Sheikh, H.H.; Mahmoud, M.S., (2009). "The use of free and immobilized *Cunninghamella elegans* for removing cobalt ions from aqueous waste solutions" World Journal of Microbiology and Biotechnology 25 (12), pp. 2137.
- 13. Abdel-Razek, S. A; Abdel-Ghany, M. T; Mahmoud, A. S; El- Sheikh, H. H. and Mahmoud, S. M., (2009). "Treatment of Liquid Hazardous Wastes By Using The Fungus *Cunninghamella elegans*." J. Rad. Res. Appl. Sci., 2(5): 890 902.
- 14. Abdel-Razek, A.S.; Mahmoud, S.A.; El-Sheikh, H.H.; Abdel-Ghany, T.M.; Mahmoud, M.S., (2008). "Studies including tolerance, affinity and capacity of certain fungal species for some toxic elements in aqueous solution" Al-Azhar Bull. Sci. Vol. 19(2) Dec. pp. 29-40.

Reviewer Activities

- Reviewer at Journal of Environmental Chemical Engineering.
- Reviewer at Polish Journal of Chemical Technology
- One of the Technical Committees of the 2016 8th International Conference on Chemical, Biological and Environmental Engineering (ICBEE 2016) will be held during September 24-26, 2016 in Toronto, Canada.
- Reviewer at the Research on Chemical Intermediates (RINT), June, 2016.
- Reviewer at the Brazilian Archives of Biology and Technology, March, 2016.
- Scientific and Technical Committee & Editorial Review Board Member at World Academy of Science, Engineering and Technology, February 14, 2015.
- Reviewer at International Conference on Agricultural and Biological Sciences (ABS2015).

<u>Memberships</u>

- Member of American Chemical Society Membership No.: 31183815.
- Member of Ocean Expert (Directory of Marine and Freshwater Professionals).

Mohamed Said Mahmoud, PhD (M.S. Mahmoud)

- Membership of the American Association for Science and Technology (AASCIT), Membership No.: 1005303.
- Membership of the Royal Society of Chemistry (RSC) Membership number: 577081.
- Membership of We The Microbiologist (WTM), India.
- Membership of the International Association of Engineers (IAENG) Membership number: 161506.
- Membership of the New York Academy of Sciences.
- Membership of International Association of Hydrological Sciences (IAHS) Number: 15118. UK.
- Membership of the International Society for Environmental Information Sciences (ISEIS), Canada.
- Membership of Society of Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry (SETAC) in Africa
- Membership of Egyptian scientific syndicate.

Skills

English Languages: AMIDEAST/ CAIRO – 31/7/2006

SCALED SCORES

LISTENING COMPREHENSION : 47 STRUCTURE & WRITTEN EXPRESSION : 48 READING COMPREHENSION : 48 TOEFL TOTAL SCORE : 477

Computer: Awarded the International Computer Driving License (ICDL) Certificate include Concepts of Information Technology (IT), Using the Computer and Managing Files, Word Processing, Spreadsheets, Database, Presentation and Information and Communication (10/2010). **Skill Card Number: EGY000264348.**

Programming: Microcal Origin 5.0, Minitab 15 and SPSS for statistical analysis

Training Courses

- 1. Training course on "YZU Training Program of Molecular Biology Experimental Technology" in the period 15/11/2015 05/12/2015 at College of Bioscience and Biotechnology, Yangzhou University, Yangzhou, Jiangsu, China.
- 2. Training course on "Gas Chromatography" in the period 03/06/2012 14/06/2012 at National Research Center (NRC).
- 3. Training course in "Nanoscience and Nanotechnology" Held from 5Th to 7Th April 2011 at Nanoscience and Nanotechnology unit Beni-Suef University.
- 4. Environmental Friendly Infrastructure Training Course, Cairo Egypt October 18-22, 2010.
- 5. Fundamental principals and concepts for the International Standard ISO 9001:2008 and its Implementation from National Quality Institute (NQI) Egypt 2010.
- 6. Advanced Wastewater Management of the Egypt Urban Development program from UNESCO-IHE (Institute for Water Education) 2009.
- 7. Medical analysis training course Elsayed Galal Hospital Cairo Egypt 2003.

SEMINARS

- 1. Ω Metrohm Ion Chromatography & Titration seminar around "Ion Chromatography IC" produced by Agitech Technologies (Arabian Group for Integrated Technologies) Company Experts, Held in Dusit Thani Lakeview Cairo on September 15, 2014.
- 2. Agilent-Agitech spectroscopy seminar around "New Technologies of Atomic and Molecular spectroscopy" produced by Agilent Technologies Company Experts, Held in Novotel Cairo airport Hotel on March 6, 2013.

<u>WORKSHOPS</u>

Mohamed Said Mahmoud, PhD (M.S. Mahmoud)

- Participate in workshop entitled "Publishing in high ranked journals" Under auspices of Academy of Scientific Research and Technology (ASRT) and Royal Society of Chemistry (RSC), NIDOC, 3rd of May, 2015.
- 2. Participate in workshop program in TITLE: "Egyptian Standard Specification for the Analysis of Commercial Products Analysis by Chromatographic instruments (GC and GC-MS)" at Chemistry Administration, Ministry of Industry and Foreign Trade at 27th of November, 2013.
- 3. Participate in the activates of the African workshop on "The Role of Reference Materials in Water Analysis" Held in National Institute of Standards (NIS) in the Period 8-9 May 2012.

LECTURE'S DIRECTOR

Prepare and teach course material for the following

- Lecture director at National Organization for Potable water & Sanitary Drainage –
 Egypt in training Course Program (Chemical analysis for Potable water) in TITLE:
 "Potable water characterization Sampling Sample preservation Water chemical analysis and quality control" From 16 to 20 February, 2014.
- Lecture director at National Organization for Potable water & Sanitary Drainage –
 Egypt in training Course Program (Chemical analysis for wastewater) in TITLE:
 "wastewater characterization (Chemical, Physical and biological) Sampling –
 Sample preservation chemical analysis and quality control" From 17 to 21 Feb 2013.
- 3. Lecture director at National Organization for Potable water & Sanitary Drainage Egypt in training Course Program (Chemical analysis for Potable water) in TITLE: "Potable water characterization Sampling Sample preservation Water chemical analysis and quality control" From 9 to 13 December 2012.
- 4. Lecture director at UTI Housing and Building National Research Center Egypt in training Course Program (Advanced Laboratories) in TITLE: "Atomic Absorption Spectrophotometer Instrumentation and Metal analysis" From 11 to 13 January 2011.

CONFERENCES

- 1. Participated in 5th Middle East Green Building Conference & Exhibition from 20- 21 April, 2016 Sofitel El Gazirah Hotel Egypt.
- 2. Participated in Conference on Sensing, Information and Decision at the Cellular Level, from 14 17 July, 2015 at The Abdus Salam International Center for Theoretical Physics (ICTP), Trieste, Italy.
- 3. Participated in 7th International Conference On Nano-Technology In Construction, from 27 -31 March, 2015, Sharm El-Sheikh, Egypt.
- 4. Participated with oral and technical presentation in ICAE 2014: XII International Conference on Agricultural Engineering from November 25-26, 2014. International Scientific Research and Experimental Development, Dubai, UAE.
- 5. Participated with paper in the "2nd International Conference and Exhibition Sustainable Water Supply and Sanitation (SWSSC) held during 3 –5 December 2012 at the Cairo In'l Conference Center in Cairo–Egypt.
- 6. Participated in the "1st International Conference and Exhibition Sustainable Water Supply and Sanitation (SWSSC) held during 25–27 July 2010 at the Cairo In'l Conference Center in Cairo–Egypt.

OTHER ACTIVITIES

- 1. Technical Manager of Chemistry Lab at Water and Wastewater at Sanitary and Environmental Institute, Housing and Building National Research Center that attained IAS17025 2011.
- Participated as Technical Honest in Egyptian Code for design criteria and terms of execution of municipal solid wastes management systems from February 2013 till now.

Mohamed Said Mahmoud, PhD (M.S. Mahmoud)

3. Participated as Technical Honest in Egyptian Code for design criteria and terms of execution of desalination plants from January 2012 till now.

4. RESEARCH PROFILES

5. M. S. Mahmoud

Researcher at Housing and Building National Research Center

ORCID identifier	0000-0002-7224-6232
Researcher ID	A-1961-2015
Scopus Author ID	56707600400
h-indexScopus http://www.scopus.com/authid/detail.url?authorId=56707600400	2
Scopus total citations	6
Google Scholar h-index	4
Google Scholar total citations https://scholar.google.com.eg/citations?user=ppVOP IAAAAJ&hl=en	32

REFERENCES

Ashraf Aly Hassan, Ph.D., P.E.

Senior Process Engineer BioAir Solutions, LLC 110 Kresson-Gibbsboro Road, Suite 303 Voorhees, NJ 08043, USA.

hosniaa@mail.uc.edu

Mohamed K. Mostafa, Ph.D.,

Research Associate at Department of Civil, Construction, and Environmental Engineering, University of Alabama at Birmingham, 1075 13th Street South, Birmingham, AL 35294-4440, phone: (205)-540-0550, USA.

mkhaled@uab.edu

Professor Titus A.M. Msagati

College of Science Engineering and Technology, University of South Africa (UNISA), The Science Campus P/Bag X6,Cnr Christiaan De wet and Pioneer Avenue, Florida Park, Roodepoort 1709, Johannesburg, Office Tel: +27 22 670 9482, Mobile Tel: +27 72 311 0693, South Africa.

msagatam@unisa.ac.za

Professor Giuliano Degrassi, PhD

Coordinator, Industrial Biotechnology Group IBIOBA-ICGEB International Centre for Genetic Engineering and Biotechnology Polo Científico Tecnológico Godoy Cruz 2390, C1425FQD, Bs. As., Argentina, Italy.

degrassi@icgeb.org

Professor Ewald Hettema, PhD

Department of Molecular Biology and Biotechnology at University of Sheffield, UK.

E.Hettema@sheffield.ac.u

Professor Maha Moustafa El-Shafai

Professor at sanitary and environmental Engineering institute, Housing and Building National Research Center, Egypt.

m_elshafai@yahoo.com

Professor Gamila Hussin

Professor of water contaminants at National Research Center, Egypt.

gamilaali2003@gmail.com

Professor Ademola Olaniran

Professor at the School of Life Sciences. Telephone: +27 31 260 7400. Fax: +27 31 260 7809, South Africa.

olanirana@ukzn.ac.za